Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/iainljbrown (LinkedIn) blogs.sas.com/content/author/ iainbrown/ (Blog) medium.com/@lainLJBrown (Blog)

Top Skills

Data Science Artificial Intelligence (AI) Machine Learning

Honors-Awards

Associate Fellow of the Operational Research Society (AFORS)
SAS Student Ambassador 2011

Publications

Benchmarking regression algorithms for loss given default modeling

Developing Credit Risk Models
Using SAS Enterprise Miner and
SAS/STAT: Theory and Applications

An experimental comparison of classification algorithms for imbalanced credit scoring data sets

Exposure at default models with and without the credit conversion factor

Regression Model Development for Credit Card Exposure At Default (EAD) using SAS/STAT and SAS Enterprise Miner

Iain Brown Ph.D.

Head of Data Science | Adjunct Professor | Author | LinkedIn 5x Top Voice | DataIQ100 | Credit500

Marlow, England, United Kingdom

Summary

Dr. Iain Brown (Twitter: @IainLJBrown) is the Head of Data Science for Northern Europe and Adjunct Professor of Marketing Data Science at University of Southampton. For over a decade he has worked across a variety of sectors, providing thought leadership on the topics of Risk, Marketing, AI and Machine Learning.

During his career he has been involved in delivering numerous projects, and driving innovation in the fields of AI and the corresponding fields of machine learning, deep learning and natural language understanding.

As an experienced public speaker and published author he has presented at internationally renowned conferences and has papers published in the European Journal of Operational Research, International Journal of Forecasting and the Journal of Expert Systems with Applications on the aforementioned areas of expertise.

Opinions are my own.

Experience

SAS

12 years 3 months

Head of Data Science, Northern Europe June 2023 - Present (6 months)

Marlow, England, United Kingdom

As the Head of Data Science for Northern Europe or NERDS (Northern Europe Region Data Science), my role revolves around fostering an innovative and collaborative data science culture across the region. I am responsible for driving the strategic direction and providing thought leadership to businesses on the effective utilisation of advanced data analytics techniques including Machine Learning, Deep Learning, and Natural Language Understanding.

Leading a diverse team of multidisciplinary data scientists across all verticals, my goal is to facilitate synergy within the team and encourage the development and sharing of best practices. The diversity of the team not only spans across different areas of expertise but also different cultures and perspectives, which contributes to creating well-rounded and comprehensive solutions.

My work involves translating complex data insights into actionable business strategies, ensuring that our clients and businesses can derive the maximum value from our analysis. Additionally, I am tasked with managing communication between different stakeholders, including C-suite executives, IT specialists, and other business professionals, to ensure that our data science initiatives are aligned with the broader business objectives.

Lastly, my role as NERDS' lead includes ensuring that our work adheres to ethical guidelines and data privacy regulations. By ensuring data integrity and building trustworthy AI systems, we strive to make a positive and lasting impact on businesses in the Northern Europe region.

Head of Data Science, UKI
June 2018 - June 2023 (5 years 1 month)
Marlow, Buckinghamshire, United Kingdom

Leading a diverse team of highly skilled multidisciplinary data scientists across all verticals. Providing thought leadership and strategic direction for businesses on the practical applications of Machine Learning / Deep Learning / Natural Language Understanding.

Principal Data Scientist
September 2011 - June 2018 (6 years 10 months)
Marlow, United Kingdom

As a Principal Data Scientist in the Data Science and innovation team at SAS I provide specialist analytical knowledge in the application and implementation of advanced machine learning algorithms.

This analytical knowledge helps me to work with our clients to successfully provide value-based solutions and develop strategies and goals for their successful deployment. I also demonstrate SAS and its' solutions to clients and at public events as well as conducting Proof of Concepts.

Key aspects of role:

- · Driving data science best practice and providing thought leadership
- Providing extensive domain expertise in the technology area of data science
- Undertaking both pre-sales and consulting data science projects
- Using data science as a differentiator to win and increase the value of software solutions
- Developing Intellectual property in data science for SAS UK & I

University of Southampton Adjunct Professor of Marketing Data Science February 2018 - Present (5 years 10 months) Southampton, United Kingdom

Teaching the Marketing Data Science module to MSc Marketing Analytics students at the Southampton Business School.

2022 - pres. - MANG6260 - Marketing Data Science
2021 - 2022 - MANG6528 - Digital and Media Analytics
2018 - 2021 - MANG6471 - Using Big Data for Consultancy

Lloyds Banking Group Senior Risk Analyst January 2011 - September 2011 (9 months) London, United Kingdom

As part of my role in the Risk team at LBG I was involved in applying technical analytical methods to support the development of LBG's regulatory models (including Basel PD, LGD and EAD models). I also assisted in the scoping, validation and monitoring of the risk models and provided technical leadership to junior analysts.

My key responsibilities included taking the lead on critical business testing for the Loans portfolio models. I also developed and presented material on Basel compliancy to new starters at the company.

University of Southampton Business School Researcher and Lecturer October 2007 - January 2011 (3 years 4 months) Southampton, United Kingdom

Throughout the duration of my doctoral research I taught modules in Stats and programming to MSc students studying Marketing Analytics, Operational Research and Finance at the University of Southampton.

UK Export Finance Research Internship June 2007 - September 2007 (4 months)

As part of my Operational Research MSc at the London School of Economics I undertook a research internship at the Export Credits Guarantee Department (ECGD) now UK Export Finance. The project involved researching statistical software packages that could be implemented for data analysis within the department.

Education

University of Southampton Ph.D., Risk Modelling · (2007 - 2011)

The London School of Economics and Political Science (LSE) MSc, Operational Research · (2006 - 2007)

University of Kent BSc, Applied Statistics · (2003 - 2006)

Simon Langton Grammar School for Boys (1996 - 2003)